A Guide to the Norman L. Grover Papers, 1960-1992
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Norman L. Grover Papers, 1960-1992
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1991-037
5.8 cu. ft. 5 boxes
This collection contains the papers of Norman L. Grover a former professor in the Philosophy and Religion Department(s) at Virginia Tech from 1957-1991.
Grover, Norman
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired by Special Collections in 2001.
Biographical Note
Norman L. Grover was a faculty member in the department of Philosophy and Religion and later the Department of Religion from 1957 until his retirement in 1994. He also served as head of the department from 1957-1975.
Scope and Content
This collection encompasses a wide variety of materials including documents from the Department of Philosophy and Religion, the Humanities Program, and the College of Arts and Sciences Faculty Association. The collection also contains academic publications, information concerning campus events through the years, and materials from classes offered by the Departments of Philosophy and Religion from the 1960s through the 1990s.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into series by subject type. Within each series, files are arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
Series I: University Level Administrative Materials includes papers relating to the Virginia Tech chapter of the AAUP; memos and reports from the College of Arts and Sciences, University Council, and Faculty Senate; faculty handbooks; and state employee materials. Series II: Department of Philosophy and Religion Materials contains memos; course proposals and curriculum papers; faculty meeting minutes; and administrative documents.
Series III: Philosophy Major/Department Materials consists of administrative papers collected to establish the major, as well as advising records; honors society by-laws; and faculty memos.
Series IV: Religion Major/Department Materials includes degree and major proposals; higher education files on curriculum; correspondence; and informational flyers.
Series V: Academic Publications, Drafts, and Manuscripts contains articles and writings by others collected by Grover.
Series VI: Materials from Various Conferences, Lectures, and Campus Events, consists of programs notes; advertising and informational flyers; and other papers relating to Grover’s attendance and involvement with campus, relational, and nation events.
Series VII: Philosophy and Religion Course Materials contains course and club specific papers; syllabi; handouts on Charles Darwin; and honors seminar materials.
Series VIII: Miscellaneous Documents includes individual issues of newsletters kept by Grover; non-academic articles and clippings; materials on campus organization; handouts; and other ephemera.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
This collection includes several books which have been separated from the manuscript portion of the collection. The books include:
Hawthore's Little Daffydowndilly and other Stories
Wilsson's First Reader
The Bear Cubbook
A History of Kansas by Anna E. Arnold
The American Red Cross Life Saving and Water Safety
Manual of Parliamentary Practice: Rules of Proceeding and Debate in Deliberative Assemblies by Luther S. Cushing
Morals and Dogma of the Ancient and Accepted scottish Rite of Freemasonry
Seeing Canada with Lowell Thomas
Infantry Fire; Its Use in Battle by Joseph B. Batchelor, Jr.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Faculty; Religion; University Archives; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Series I: University Level Administrative Materials, 1964-1990, n.d.
  - AAUP VA Conference Newsletters (1980s) and AAUP VA Tech Chapter Memos (Box-folder 1-1)
  - AAUP Virginia Tech Chapter Meeting Minutes, (1980s-1990s) (Box-folder 1-2)
  - AAUP Committee on Changes in Virginia Tech's Grievance Procedures, (1987) (Box-folder 1-3)
  - AAUP Miscellaneous Materials (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Administration-Faculty Retreat, (1975) (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Blacksburg "107" Fund Financial Records (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Campus Demonstrations, (1970-1971) (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Center for Programs in the Humanities Newsletter, (1985) (Box-folder 1-8)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Annual Report to the President, (1967-1968) (Box-folder 1-9)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-"Campaign for Excellence" Committee, (1984-1985) (Box-folder 1-10)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Dean's Annual Report to the Faculty, (1965-1966, 1966-1967) (Box-folder 1-11)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Department Chairs Meetings, (1964-1967) (Box-folder 1-12)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Department Chairs Meetings, (1968-1969) (Box-folder 1-13)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Faculty Association, (1966-1969) (Box-folder 1-14)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Faculty Association, (1971-1974) (Box-folder 1-15)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Faculty Association, (1975-1979) (Box-folder 1-16)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Faculty Association, (1980-1984) (Box-folder 1-17)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Faculty Association, (1985-1990) (Box-folder 1-18)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Faculty Constitution and Bylaws (Box-folder 1-19)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Memoranda, (1968-1979) (Box-folder 1-20)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Memoranda, (1980-1984) (Box-folder 1-21)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Memoranda, (1985-1990) (Box-folder 1-22)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Planning Goals and Objectives, (1988) (Box-folder 1-23)
  - College of Arts and Sciences-Role and Responsibilities of Department Heads (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Committee for Development of the Humanities (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Faculty Handbook, (1977) (Box-folder 1-26)
  - Faculty Handbook, (1983) (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Faculty Senate-Ad Hoc Faculty Survey Committee Reports, (1970) (Box-folder 1-28)
  - Faculty Senate-Proposed Constitution and Bylaws, (1968) (Box-folder 1-29)
  - Faculty Senate-Report of Committee on Campus Unrest, (1970) (Box-folder 1-30)
  - Honor System Informational Materials (Box-folder 1-31)
  - Humanities Advisory Committee (Box-folder 1-32)
  - Humanities Committee on Non-Western Areas (Box-folder 1-33)
  - Humanities Program-Mini Newsletter, (1986-1987) (Box-folder 1-34)
  - Humanities Program-Mission and Goals, (1988) (Box-folder 1-35)
  - Humanities Newsletter, (1978-1981) (Box-folder 1-36)
  - Humanities Program-Faculty Meetings, (1987) (Box-folder 1-37)
  - Humanities Program-Memoranda, (1975-1979) (Box-folder 1-38)
  - Humanities Program-Memoranda, (1981-1984) (Box-folder 1-39)
  - Humanities Program-Memoranda, (1985) (Box-folder 1-40)
  - Humanities Program-Memoranda, (1986) (Box-folder 1-41)
  - Humanities Program-Memoranda, (1987) (Box-folder 1-42)
  - Humanities Program-Memoranda, (1989) (Box-folder 1-43)
  - Humanities Program-Memoranda, (1988) (Box-folder 1-44)
  - Humanities Program-Memoranda, (1990-1991) (Box-folder 1-45)
  - Letter from Leslie F. Malpass concerning the search committee for a new dean, (December 31, 1968) (Box-folder 1-46)
  - Proposal for Interdisciplinary Humanities Program (Box-folder 1-47)
  - Student Government Association (1970-1972) (Box-folder 1-48)
  - University Council (Box-folder 1-49)
  - The University Council and the Faculty Senate Constitutions and Bylaws, (1969) (Box-folder 1-50)
  - University Council and Faculty Senate Constitutions and Bylaws, (1973) (Box-folder 1-51)
  - The University Council and Faculty Senate Constitutions and Bylaws, (1982) (Box-folder 1-52)
  - Virginia Philosophical Association-Committee on Standards for Teaching of Philosophy in Virginia Institutions of Higher Education, (1965) (Box-folder 1-53)
  - The Virginia State Employees Combined Charitable Campaign (Box-folder 1-54)
  - Virginia State Employees Combined Charitable Campaign-Volunteers Weekly Report, (1988) (Box-folder 1-55)
- Series II: Department of Philosophy and Religion Materials, 1960-1992, n.d.
  - Annual Report of the Department of Philosophy and Religion, (1973-1974) (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion Course Proposals, (1985-1987) (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion-Curriculum Committee, (1960-1968) (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion Curriculum Committee, (1970-1980) (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion-Events (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion Faculty Meetings-Folder 1 (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion Faculty Meetings-Folder 2 (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion Faculty Meetings-Folder 3 (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion Faculty Meetings-Folder 4 (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion Faculty-Folder 5 (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion Faculty Meetings-Folder 6 (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion Five Year Department Review, (1982) (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion Grade Distribution Data, (1974) (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion Memoranda and Informational Sheets, (1970-1988) (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion Memoranda, (1989-1990) (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion-Religion Committee, (1972-1982) (Box-folder 2-16)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion-Religion Faculty Memoranda, (1981-1982) (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion-Religion Faculty Meetings, (1982-1992) (Box-folder 2-18)
  - Department of Philosophy and Religion-Religion Faculty Memoranda, (1983) (Box-folder 2-19)
  - Draft of Department of Philosophy and Religion Annual Report, (1974-1975) (Box-folder 2-20)
- Series III: Philosophy Major/Department Materials, 1965-1989, n.d.
  - Advising Department-Philosophy Majors-Folder 1 (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Advising Department-Philosophy Majors-Folder 2 (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Advising Department-Philosophy Majors-Folder 3 (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Advising Department-Philosophy Major-Folder 4 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Phi Sigma Tau-Virginia Beta Chapter-Bylaws and Charter Petition, (1979) (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Philosophy Department Faculty Memoranda, (1972-1978) (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Philosophy Major Proposal, (1965-1966)- Folder 1 (Box-folder 3-7)
  - Philosophy Major Proposal, (1965-1966)-Folder 2 (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Philosophy Major Proposal-Preliminary Papers-Folder 1 (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Philosophy Major Proposal-Preliminary Papers-Folder 2 (Box-folder 3-10)
- Series IV: Religion Major/Department Materials, 1967-1991, n.d.
  - B.A. in Religious Studies Curriculum Proposal, (1973-1974) (Box-folder 3-11)
  - College of Arts and Sciences Department of Religion Five Year Review, (1990) (Box-folder 3-12)
  - Correspondence, (1967) (Box-folder 3-13)
  - Department of Religion Bachelor's Degree Proposals, (1974)-Folder 1 (Box-folder 3-14)
  - Department of Religion Bachelor's Degree Proposals, (1974)-Folder 2 (Box-folder 3-15)
  - Department of Religion Course Listings, (1989-1990) (Box-folder 3-16)
  - Department of Religion-Five Year Review, (1989) (Box-folder 3-17)
  - Department of Religion-Five Year Departmental Review, (1990) (Box-folder 3-18)
  - Department of Religion-Memoranda, (1985) (Box-folder 3-19)
  - Department of Religion-Memoranda, (1986) (Box-folder 3-20)
  - Department of Religion-Memoranda, (1987) (Box-folder 3-21)
  - Department of Religion-Memoranda, (1988) (Box-folder 3-22)
  - Department of Religion Memoranda, (1989) (Box-folder 3-23)
  - Department of Religion Memoranda, (1990-1991) (Box-folder 3-24)
  - List of Religion Majors, (1989) (Box-folder 3-25)
  - Religion Curricula in State Higher Education- Folder 1 (Box-folder 3-26)
  - Religion Curricula in State Higher Education-Folder 2 (Box-folder 3-26)
  - Religion Curricula in State Higher Education-Folder 3 (Box-folder 3-28)
  - Religion Major Informational Flyers (Box-folder 3-29)
- Series V: Academic Publications, Drafts, and Manuscripts, c.1960s-1990s
  - Articles concerning Religious Studies in Higher Education (Box-folder 3-30)
  - "The Black Man in the cave in Chapultepec: An Aztec Variant on the Gatekeeper Motif" by Franke J. Neumann in Religious Encounters with Death (Box-folder 3-31)
  - Book Reviews (Box-folder 3-32)
  - "Building a Department of Religious Studies in the 80s" (Box-folder 3-33)
  - "Concience-less Society and Beyond Perspectives from Erich From and Paul Tillich" by Guy B. Hammond in Neue Zeitschrift Fur Systemastiche Theologie und Religionsphilosophie (Box-folder 3-34)
  - "Development of a Lamp in Palestine" by Charles A. Kennedy (Box-folder 3-35)
  - Draft: "The Myth of the Neutral Man" by Janice Moulton (Box-folder 3-36)
  - "The Dragon and the Dog: Two Symbols of Time in Nahuatl Religion" by Franke J. Neumann in Numen (Box-folder 3-37)
  - "An Examination of Tillich's Method of Correlation" by Guyton B. Hammond in the Journal of Bible and Religion (Box-folder 3-38)
  - "The Flayed God and His Rattlestick: A Shamanic Element in Pre-Hispanic Mesoamerican Religion" by Franke J. Neumann in History of Religion (Box-folder 3-39)
  - "Hempel Versus Sellars on Explanation" by Joseph C. Pitt in Dialectica (Box-folder 3-40)
  - "Immediacy and Distance in Religion" by Edward Leroy Lon, Jr. in The New Drew Gateway (Box-folder 4-1)
  - "Knowledge, Justification, and Reliability" by Frederick F. Schmitt (Box-folder 4-2)
  - "Metaphilosophical Classification" by Palmer C. Talbutt, Jr. in Teaching Philosophy (Box-folder 4-3)
  - "Modal Elaborations of Propositional Logics" by Nicolas Rescher and Ruth Manor in Notre Dame Journal of Formal Logic (Box-folder 4-4)
  - "Objects of Dianoia in Plato's Divided Line" by Nicholas D. Smith in Apeiron (Box-folder 4-5)
  - "Paper: A Sacred Material in Aztec Ritual" by Franke J. Neumann in History of Religion (Box-folder 4-6)
  - "Paul Tillich's Critique of Humanism" by Guy B. Hammond in Religious Humanism (Box-folder 4-7)
  - "The Recovery of Distance" by Guy B. Hammond in the Journal of Religion (Box-folder 4-8)
  - "Relativism and Nihilism" by Tom Carson (Box-folder 4-9)
  - "Religious Studies in Higher Education" (Box-folder 4-10)
  - "Science, Ethics, and the States of Cetaceans" by Harlan B. Miller (Box-folder 4-11)
  - "The Scholarly Study of Religion in College and University" by Robert Michaelson (Box-folder 4-12)
  - "A Simple Cure for Grade Inflation" by Irving John Good in the Journal of Educational Data Processing (Box-folder 4-13)
  - "Socrates' Proposed Penalty in Plato's Apology" by Thomas C. Brickhouse and Nicholas D. Smith in Archiv Fur Geschichte der Philosophie (Box-folder 4-14)
  - "Structuralism, Hermeneutics, and Contextual Meaning" by Elizabeth Struthers Malbon i Journal o American Academy of Religion (Box-folder 4-15)
  - "The Study of Religion on the Campus of Today" ed. by Karl D. Hartzell (Box-folder 4-16)
  - Techniques and Applications of Symbolic Logic by Charles E. Cardwell (Box-folder 4-17)
  - "Theology and the Gentile Tradition" by Palmer C. Talbutt, Jr. (Box-folder 4-18)
  - Transfiguration Manuscript by Frank Burch Brown (Box-folder 4-19)
  - "The Untrodden Road: Rationality and Galileo's Theory of the Tides" buy Joseph C. Pitt in Nature and System (Box-folder 4-20)
  - "The Varieties of Truth" bu Perry C. Holt in Journal of the Tn Academy of Science (Box-folder 4-21)
  - "Voter Education in Raleigh" by Robert W. Catlett (Box-folder 4-22)
- Series VI: Materials from Various Conferences, Lectures, and Campus Events, 1960-1986, n.d.
  - American Academy of Religion-Southeastern Region Meeting Papers and Correspondence, (March 13-15, 1980) (Box-folder 4-23)
  - Conference on Religious Emphasis, (1963) (Box-folder 4-24)
  - Ethics in Higher Education ("Education for Ethical Conduct" A Conference Brochure and "Renewed Interest in Ethics in Higher Education by Dr. Edward Leroy Long, Jr.) (Box-folder 4-25)
  - Dr. Harlow Shapely's Visit to VPI, (1962) (Box-folder 4-26)
  - Lecture: Dan Garber "Mind, Body, and the Laws of Nature in Descartes and Leibniz," (April 14, 1983) (Box-folder 4-27)
  - Informational Materials from VPI Campus Events, (1960s-1980s) (Box-folder 4-28)
  - The Morality of Communications: Education Lecture-Discussion (Box-folder 4-29)
  - Nuclear Winter: Strategic and Diplomatic Implications, (March 6, 1986) (Box-folder 4-30)
  - Program for 1984 Annual Meeting of the VPA (Box-folder 4-31)
  - Dr. Tipton R. Snavely's Visit as Part of the Visiting Scholar Program, (1964) (Box-folder 4-32)
  - VPI and SU Administrative Conferences (Box-folder 4-33)
- Series VII: Philosophy and Religion Course Materials, 1971-1972, n.d.
  - Charles Darwin Handouts (Box-folder 4-34)
  - Freshman Honors Seminar (1971) VPI Philosophy and Religion Department (Box-folder 4-35)
  - Freshmen Honors Seminar (1972) VPI Philosophy and Religion Department (Box-folder 4-36)
  - Humanities: The Modern World Materials (Box-folder 4-37)
  - Phenomenology of Religion Course Syllabus (Box-folder 4-38)
  - The Philosophy Club (Box-folder 4-39)
  - Miscellaneous Philosophy Course Materials (Box-folder 4-40)
  - Religion and the Modern World (Box-folder 4-41)
- Series VIII: Miscellaneous Documents, 1967-1979, n.d.
  - Arete Newsletters (Center for Programs in the Humanities) (Box-folder 4-42)
  - Blacksburg Free Press Paper, (November 25, 1968) (Box-folder 4-43)
  - Crisis Center Informational Handout (Box-folder 5-1)
  - "Ethics in America" Viewer's Guide (Box-folder 5-2)
  - "The Humanist Speaks" Radio Series, (1972) (Box-folder 5-3)
  - "Initial Draft of a Proposed Brief Statement of Reformed Faith for Response by the Church" (Box-folder 5-4)
  - It's Academic Newsletter, (October 1989) (Box-folder 5-5)
  - "Laments of a Teacher" -Poem by Paul Derring (Box-folder 5-6)
  - Letter to Robert Stephenson from Alfred C. Payne with Bibiliography of Religious Periodicals in VPI's Library, (1972) (Box-folder 5-7)
  - Techgram, (April 1966) (Box-folder 5-8)
  - Article About UFO Research and "A Consumer's Guide to Pseudoscience" (Box-folder 5-9)
  - Virginia Tech Spectrum, (January 18, 1979) (Box-folder 5-10)
  - The Virginia Wreck, (May 26, 1967) (Box-folder 5-11)
  - "Marks of Maturity" from Oral Roberts University (Box-folder 5-12)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Articles (Box-folder 5-13)
  - Outline of Gay Student Alliance Organization (Box-folder 5-14)
  - The Passion According to St. John Performance (Box-folder 5-15)
  - Teaching and Learning Newsletters (Box-folder 5-16)